<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Johnathan Coker &#8211; gofuneral</title>
	<atom:link href="https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/author/forwinder/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/</link>
	<description>Just another WordPress site</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 16:58:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>What Do You Do At A Visitation?</title>
		<link>https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/what-do-you-do-at-a-visitation/</link>
					<comments>https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/what-do-you-do-at-a-visitation/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Johnathan Coker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 02:27:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/?p=27</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You&#8217;ve decided to go to the visitation but you aren&#8217;t sure what to do when you get there. That&#8217;s not uncommon. Each and every family grieves differently and it can]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>You&#8217;ve decided to go to the visitation but you aren&#8217;t sure what to do when you get there. That&#8217;s not uncommon. Each and every family grieves differently and it can sometimes be hard to determine what&#8217;s expected of you. Let&#8217;s talk about it.</p>



<p><em>What do I do at a visitation?</em> <strong>You pay your respects to the surviving family. 1. Condolences. Greet those who have experienced loss and offer them your sympathy. 2. Relationships. Spend time meeting new people and reminiscing with those you know. 3. Gifts. Ask the staff at the funeral home where to place any gifts you&#8217;ve brought. 4. Decorum. Be sure not to make a spectacle of yourself. 5. Leave. Show respect by not overstaying your welcome.</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="828" height="812" src="https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/whatdoyu.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-28" srcset="https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/whatdoyu.jpeg 828w, https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/whatdoyu-300x294.jpeg 300w, https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/whatdoyu-768x753.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 828px) 100vw, 828px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<h2><strong>&#8220;I am so sorry for your loss&#8221;</strong></h2>



<p>Some families have extremely different ways of approaching death and we want to be sensitive to that. However, you can have confidence that if the visitation has been scheduled, then the family wants everyone to have the opportunity for closure.</p>



<p>&#8220;Visitation&#8221; simply means the family that has experienced loss has set aside a specific time for any friends, extended family, and/or acquaintances to &#8220;pay their respects&#8221;.</p>



<p>Another way to see a visitation may be to look at it sort of like a church service. Churches typically do not send out a personal invitation to people, however, they do post their service times for everyone to know. This is because everyone is welcome to come during those times.</p>



<p>You have full access to all of the church&#8217;s faculties during that time frame as well. It is much the same as a &#8220;visitation&#8221;. The funeral home has worked with the grieving family to establish a time where you are welcome to come and participate.</p>



<p>&#8220;Participate in what?&#8221; you may ask. Participate in &#8220;paying your respects&#8221; to the family of the departed. That may look a little different for each family and in some cases, the atmosphere may be somber and very grievous. In others, it may celebratory.</p>



<p>You will need to be sensitive to that &#8220;feeling&#8221; as you arrive and begin making your way to greet the family. A few good questions to ask yourself before you arrive are:</p>



<ul><li><strong>How old was the departed?</strong></li><li><strong>How did the departed pass?</strong></li><li><strong>Was the passing expected or unexpected?</strong></li></ul>



<p>Asking yourself those questions will give you a good idea of what to expect the atmosphere to be like. I say that as a general rule but it is a safe way to make sure you are as respectful as possible. You want to make sure you err on the side of &#8220;respectful&#8221;.</p>



<p>Our goal is to convey our sympathy to the family in a kind and honorable way. We do not want to create an unintended offense by being insensitive to the level of grief the family is feeling. We are there to be supportive. Not instructive. Leave that to the ministers.</p>



<h2><strong>&#8220;I haven&#8217;t seen you in a month of Sundays&#8221;</strong></h2>



<p>One of the very best things for you to plan to do while at the visitation is to spend time catching up with those you haven&#8217;t seen in a while. A familiar face is nearly always a welcome comfort in times of grief.</p>



<p>You may carry a memory of the departed with you that the family is very fond of. On seeing you that memory will comfort them. Make it your business to be available to reminisce with those who are grieving.</p>



<p>Talking is an excellent way to handle a loss. Now look, don&#8217;t be that person that walks around interrupting and forcing conversations with people. I&#8217;ll touch on being obnoxious in a little bit. You simply want to make yourself available to anyone who may want to share stories with you.</p>



<p>There will likely be others at the visitation that you have never seen before in your entire life. Chances are they are feeling a little uncomfortable the same as you. They may be unsure of what to say or how to say it. This would be a great opportunity to make their acquaintance.</p>



<p>A comforting sight to a grieving family is to see those who came to pay their respects standing around talking to one another. It gives a sense of catharsis to know that their departed loved one had so many friends and acquaintances.</p>



<p><strong>It&#8217;s never a good idea to show up, shake hands, eat cake, and then leave.</strong>Be polite. Have several conversations with folks you may not know. They may need to talk as much as the family who experienced loss. You never know. Everyone gets closure in their own way.</p>



<p>Now, remember we are primarily here to &#8220;pay our respects&#8221; not to mingle and hobnob. I&#8217;m not telling you to &#8220;work the room&#8221; like you&#8217;re campaigning for office. I&#8217;m merely saying that you should be available to show love to those who need it and be willing to be loved in return.</p>



<h2><strong>I brought a cake!</strong></h2>



<p>Ok, this is a pet peeve of mine so please give me some grace here. Please please do not burst through the doors and announce that you&#8217;ve brought cake. It&#8217;s a very nice thing to bring gifts to the visitation but don&#8217;t sound a trumpet before yourself.</p>



<p>I would advise that you do the very opposite of that and very discreetly ask a member of the funeral home staff where the gifts go. They will be able to tell you exactly what to do.</p>



<p>The staff is there to take care of such things for the family so they may grieve with as few disturbances as possible. In fact, most of the things you will encounter at a visitation have been arranged by the family and performed by the funeral home staff behind the scenes.</p>



<p>Now, what kind of gifts are appropriate for a visitation? Well, here are a few. I would stay pretty close to this list:</p>



<ul><li><strong>Flowers</strong>&nbsp;&#8211; the colors are not extra important</li><li><strong>Cards</strong>&nbsp;&#8211; very appropriate for friends and acquaintances</li><li><strong>Food</strong>&nbsp;&#8211; finger foods are the most appropriate</li></ul>



<p>If you have an heirloom that you want to return to the family or some other special kind of gift, present it to the family in a different setting. The visitation is not the appropriate time to bring a flag or medal of honor.</p>



<p>Those types of items should be given to the family soon after the death sometime before the visitation if possible. If not, you may want to try and get your gift to them between the visitation and the funeral if you can. If that can not be arranged, wait till a later date.</p>



<h2><strong>This is about the family</strong></h2>



<p>The reason I suggest being so discreet in both your interactions and the presenting of your gifts is because we don&#8217;t want to draw attention to ourselves. The focus should remain on the family and the departed.</p>



<p>Some folks will use the visitation time as an opportunity to make a spectacle of themselves. You&#8217;ve seen this before I am sure. We do not want to be the obnoxious person arguing about politics in the hall so loudly the family can&#8217;t hear the folks greeting them near the casket.</p>



<p>It is a comforting thing to hear friends and family laughing and talking. So please don&#8217;t hear me in the wrong way. There is a line that you have to be sensitive to that is not always that obvious. The best thing to do is err on the side of &#8220;respectful&#8221;.</p>



<p>Here&#8217;s a checklist of things that may help you figure this out:</p>



<ul><li>Are you dressed appropriately and conservatively?</li><li>Are you speaking at a normal volume?</li><li>Are your jokes appropriate for mixed company?</li><li>Are you leaving enough food for other people?</li><li>Are you being brief and quiet in the viewing room?</li><li>Are you going outside to smoke?</li><li>Are you sober, shaved, and groomed?</li></ul>



<p>Some of those may seem ridiculous but you would be surprised. Remember that this moment is about the family and the departed and not about you. Lay aside any &#8220;agenda&#8221; you may have and simply be there for them. You will have time to work out things or give special gifts later.</p>



<h2><strong>So long, farewell</strong></h2>



<p>So now it&#8217;s time to go. You have made your way around the funeral home several times and you&#8217;ve been to the viewing room a couple of times as well. Be respectful as you exit and say goodbye to anyone you may pass by and leave.</p>



<p>Now, if you have received an invitation to attend the funeral it may be appropriate for you to stay long enough to find out some of the details. In some cases, the family will extend the opportunity to attend the funeral to everyone present.</p>



<p>If that is the case, there will likely be a bulletin of some kind showing the order of events. If there is not, a member of the funeral home staff can give you any information you require.</p>



<p>The point is that we do not want to be going in and out of the viewing room like we own the place or &#8220;hanging around&#8221; unnecessarily. If you have &#8220;paid your respects&#8221; and visited for a little while, then you have likely done what you have come to do.</p>



<p>Visitations can be exhausting for the family because each person represents another memory for them to process. <strong>We want to be sensitive to that.</strong>&nbsp;After all, the family still has the funeral to do.</p>



<p>Again, all families handle grief differently. You may be asked to stay as long as you like. Just remember to be &#8220;respectful&#8221; and not overstay your welcome. If you pay attention to the atmosphere, you will know when it&#8217;s time to go.</p>



<p>So, I hope that helps you to know how you should approach a visitation. This is your chance to say goodbye so take the opportunity to do so. If you have more questions, do not hesitate to ask us.&nbsp;<strong>We are here to serve you.</strong></p>



<p>&#8220;Blessed are those who mourn, for they shall be comforted&#8221; &#8211; Matt 5:4</p>



<p>Article contributed by: Jason Coker</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/what-do-you-do-at-a-visitation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Should I Go To Both The Visitation And The Funeral?</title>
		<link>https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/should-i-go-to-both-the-visitation-and-the-funeral/</link>
					<comments>https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/should-i-go-to-both-the-visitation-and-the-funeral/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Johnathan Coker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 02:22:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/?p=21</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sometimes it can be difficult to decide whether to go to both the visitation and the funeral. You may have been close to the individual who passed but not close]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Sometimes it can be difficult to decide whether to go to both the visitation and the funeral. You may have been close to the individual who passed but not close to the family or visa versa. What if you are an estranged family member or a close friend of the family but not the departed? Let&#8217;s talk about it.</p>



<p><em>Should I go to both the visitation and the funeral?</em> <strong>When it is appropriate, yes you should go to both. 1. You were very close to the individual who passed. 2. You were invited to attend both. 3. You are very close to the individual&#8217;s family. 4. You have been asked to participate in the service. 5. You are an immediate family relation.</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-gallery columns-1 is-cropped"><ul class="blocks-gallery-grid"><li class="blocks-gallery-item"><figure><img loading="lazy" width="822" height="796" src="https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/bothfun.jpeg" alt="" data-id="22" data-full-url="https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/bothfun.jpeg" data-link="https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/?attachment_id=22" class="wp-image-22" srcset="https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/bothfun.jpeg 822w, https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/bothfun-300x291.jpeg 300w, https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/bothfun-768x744.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 822px) 100vw, 822px" /></figure></li></ul></figure>



<p></p>



<h2><strong>“We were really good friends”</strong></h2>



<p>This is where most people are confused about whether they should go to both services, I think. It&#8217;s not always easy to know what the family of the deceased expects from the friends of the deceased.</p>



<p>I believe that a good rule of thumb is to remember that a &#8220;visitation&#8221; is exactly what it means. A family has provided the chance for friends, extended family, and acquaintances to &#8220;visit&#8221; and &#8220;pay their respects&#8221;.</p>



<p>Two key phrases to remember:</p>



<ul><li>&#8220;Pay their respects&#8221;</li><li>“Pay your respects”</li></ul>



<p>You want to keep that in mind when thinking about whether you should attend the actual funeral. Some families may find it &#8220;dis-respectful&#8221; and we certainly don&#8217;t want to convey that.</p>



<p>Now, that&#8217;s not to say you should not attend the &#8220;visitation&#8221;. As I said earlier, this is the function of a visitation. The funeral is typically reserved for family and those especially close to the family of the deceased.</p>



<p>If you are not sure if you are close enough to the family to attend the funeral, it may be wise not to assume you are welcome. The key to &#8220;paying your respects&#8221; is to make sure you are indeed being respectful.</p>



<p>So what is the best approach? Go to the visitation and pay your respects to the family of your friend. Do not make presumptions but ask if you may attend the funeral. At this point, simply keep your ears open to an invitation.</p>



<p>In a lot of cases, families are not always aware of all the friendships their departed loved ones had. If you convey the nature of your relationship to them while &#8220;paying your respects&#8221; they may extend an invitation to the funeral.</p>



<p>It may be more subtle than; &#8220;We cordially invite you&#8221;. I would expect it to be somewhere in the ballpark of; &#8220;Are you planning to attend services?&#8221; or &#8220;Oh! We did not realize you were so close. We would be honored if you would attend the service.&#8221;</p>



<p>Every family handles grief differently and even the will of the deceased can influence the nature of the service. But as a general rule, most families do not want to deprive a close relationship of their departed loved one of having closure in any way.</p>



<h2><strong>Do not turn down the invitation</strong></h2>



<p>Now, if you have received an invitation to both services then you need to go. In some cases, the family will have selected special friends and acquaintances they would like to attend both the visitation and the funeral.</p>



<p>If the family has gone through the trouble to do this, then your presence isn&#8217;t simply being requested. In a way, the family is telling you that they would like to share this moment in their life with you.</p>



<p>You will have a special opportunity to minister to the family members in this situation. Your relationship with the departed has earned you the right to be present and to be heard.</p>



<p>This is an extraordinary opportunity for you to &#8220;love your neighbor as yourself&#8221;. You may find yourself in a position to offer comfort through scripture, listening, poems, sharing stories, or simply being a shoulder to cry on.</p>



<p>Lastly, it will give you the chance to have closure in a way you may not have had otherwise. The experience of bonding with your friend&#8217;s family will be something you cherish for the rest of your life. &#8220;Blessed are those who mourn. For they shall be comforted.&#8221;</p>



<h2><strong>“I am very close to the parents”</strong></h2>



<p>You may find yourself in all three of these categories if you qualify for this one. Perhaps you are the best friend of an immediate family member but were merely acquainted with the departed.</p>



<p>In cases like these, it is wisest to simply ask your friend if they would like you to attend both the visitation and the funeral. It would not be wise to assume that is the case. Even if you are best friends.</p>



<p>Having said that, plan to at least attend the &#8220;visitation&#8221;. Again, the purpose of the visitation is to provide friends, extended family, and acquaintances the opportunity to &#8220;pay their respects&#8221;.</p>



<p>If you up and decide to attend the funeral without asking your friend&#8217;s permission first you may cause an unintended offense. In some cases, this can cause problems for your friends with their family members.</p>



<p>As I said earlier, err on the side of caution if you are unsure. There is nothing wrong with asking your friend in private if you may attend both services. I expect it will be the exception that you are told no.</p>



<p>But again, every family processes loss differently so do not make assumptions. I would say you would be right to expect an invitation from a really close friend in cases where they have lost a child or spouse.</p>



<p>In those circumstances, most people want their strongest relationships near them for support. If you find yourself in a situation where you are that person, go and be available the entire time.</p>



<h2><strong>“I&#8217;m a pallbearer”</strong></h2>



<p>What if you&#8217;ve been invited to participate in the service in some way? Then you are obligated to fulfill your responsibility in an honorable and respectful manner.</p>



<p>That would mean attending both the visitation and the funeral. Also, you need to make sure that you are on time, well dressed, and available to the family in whatever capacity they may need you to serve.</p>



<p>There are several different ways that you could be asked to participate in. Here are a few:</p>



<ul><li>Greet &#8211; you could be asked to help the family receive guests during the visitation.</li><li>Singing and Poems &#8211; you may be asked to sing or read a poem during the service.</li><li>Eulogy &#8211; you may be asked to deliver the eulogy</li><li>Pallbearer &#8211; you may be asked to be a pallbearer.</li><li>Prayer &#8211; You may be asked to pray</li><li>Procession &#8211; you may be asked to participate in the funeral procession</li></ul>



<p>If you have been asked to participate in the service in any way and you have accepted, then be sure to approach your role with the same attitude of &#8220;paying your respects&#8221; as I mentioned earlier.</p>



<p><strong>The family has given you a great responsibility.</strong>&nbsp;Be very mindful of how you handle yourself. The last thing we want to do is cause harm to a family that is already grieving a loss.</p>



<p>As an added note, if you foresee any event or scheduling problem that will cause you to be unable to fulfill your obligation then you should respectfully decline. There is no dishonor in this. Quite the opposite.</p>



<p>Now, do try your best to attend the visitation any way you can. If your schedule does remain unchanged, request to attend the funeral as well. Being invited to participate in the service has earned you the right to ask.</p>



<h2><strong>Immediate family only, please</strong></h2>



<p>We are going to wrap here. I believe it is wise for all immediate family members to be at both the visitation and the funeral. Now, I say this with grace because some folks do not handle funerals well.</p>



<p>In other circumstances, there may be unresolved conflict in the family as well. In those cases, reconciliation should be pursued before the visitation or the funeral if possible. Not during the funeral.</p>



<p>It is never a good idea to go to the visitation or the funeral if you intend to have a &#8220;confrontation&#8221;. The time to do that is before if you can. Reconcile with whomever, if there is a need to, and then move on.</p>



<p>If you are the type that just can not handle funerals, then it may be best to &#8220;pay your respects&#8221; from a distance or in-person before or after the funeral. Bringing libations with you to help you get through would not be wise.</p>



<p>In both of these cases just remember that you are immediate family and your presence is likely most welcome and desired by the rest of the family. Regardless of the past. There are exceptions of course.</p>



<p>However, as I said earlier, most families do not want to deprive anyone of closure. Especially an immediate family member. Chances are, they are wanting a chance to reconcile as much as you do. Maybe more.</p>



<p>This is a time for everyone in the family to come together and comfort one another and be comforted by those closest to them.&nbsp;<strong>It&#8217;s a time for forgiveness, reconciliation, hope, and love.</strong></p>



<p>Remember, this is your opportunity to &#8220;pay your respects&#8221;. If you keep that in mind, you will make the wisest decision about whether to attend both services or not. Also, never be afraid to ask us your questions.&nbsp;<strong>We are here to serve you.</strong></p>



<p>&#8220;Blessed are those who mourn, for they shall be comforted. &#8211; Matt 5:4</p>



<p>Article contributed by: Jason Coker</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/should-i-go-to-both-the-visitation-and-the-funeral/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>10 Essential Pointers To Be An Excellent Pallbearer</title>
		<link>https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/10-essential-pointers-to-be-an-excellent-pallbearer/</link>
					<comments>https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/10-essential-pointers-to-be-an-excellent-pallbearer/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Johnathan Coker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 01:35:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/?p=12</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Being a pallbearer is a big responsibility. One that requires some forethought. It&#8217;s not always easy to know exactly how you should handle yourself or what is expected of you]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Being a pallbearer is a big responsibility. One that requires some forethought. It&#8217;s not always easy to know exactly how you should handle yourself or what is expected of you in these situations. That&#8217;s what we are here for. We can equip you with the knowledge of how to be an excellent pallbearer in honor of your loved one. Let&#8217;s talk about it.</p>



<p><strong><em>How to can I be a great pallbearer?</em>&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>Fulfill your role during the visitation and funeral while being punctual, respectful, and professional. 1. Accept or decline the invitation to participate based on your availability. 2. Get a haircut. Make sure you are properly groomed for the occasion. 3. Get a suit. Make sure you are properly dressed. 4. No new girlfriends. Unless you are in a long-standing relationship, engaged, or married plan to attend alone. 5. On-time. Do not show up late for any part of this occasion. 6. Instructions. Get directions from the funeral home staff on the order of events. 7. Serve. Be available to assist in any capacity as you are needed. 8. Etiquette. Do not make a spectacle of yourself. 9. Pay attention. Don&#8217;t get distracted and miss your ques. 10. Say goodbye. Make sure to stay a few minutes after the graveside service.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="822" height="808" src="https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/pallbearer.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-13" srcset="https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/pallbearer.jpeg 822w, https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/pallbearer-300x295.jpeg 300w, https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/pallbearer-768x755.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 822px) 100vw, 822px" /></figure>



<h2><strong>Congratulations! Now what?</strong></h2>



<p>So you&#8217;ve been selected to be a pallbearer. Well, first take a deep breath.&nbsp;<strong>This is an honor for you and a memory you will cherish for years to come.</strong>&nbsp;Let&#8217;s not let worry turn this experience into a horrible memory.</p>



<p><strong>It is not terribly difficult to be a PB.</strong>&nbsp;You just need to remember a few simple things. If you are wondering what it is exactly that being a pallbearer entails I will explain it very quickly.</p>



<p>A PB is someone who has been selected by the family to help carry the casket from the funeral home to the hearse and then from the hearse to the gravesite. Typically, there are six people selected for this role.</p>



<p>There are times when there may be one or two extra PBs walking out in front of the casket as the other six carry it. These individuals are referred to as &#8220;Honorary Pallbearers&#8221;.</p>



<p>They simply &#8220;escort&#8221; the casket.&nbsp;<strong>There is no set number of PBs that a family can select but it is pretty common to have six to eight for the average funeral.</strong>&nbsp;It will depend greatly on the arrangements and type of burial that the family has selected.</p>



<p>In a memorial service where there are ashes from someone who has been cremated, there may be a special person selected to carry the urn. This function is similar to a traditional PB.</p>



<p>You only need to understand which role you will be performing and what the order of events is for the ceremony.&nbsp;<strong>The funeral home staff will assist you with this so don&#8217;t sweat the details.</strong>&nbsp;I will go through all of that a little later.</p>



<p>So without further delay let&#8217;s get onto the business of making sure that you have the tools to be the best pallbearer you can be.</p>



<h2><strong>1. Accept or Decline</strong></h2>



<p>Hopefully, you did this before you accepted the honor of being a PB. Selecting or finding people to do this can be a task for some families. Either there are too many people to choose from or not enough.</p>



<p>In both circumstances, people&#8217;s schedules play a big part in these decisions. It&#8217;s not always possible for every person to get time off work or rearrange their life to attend these occasions. You want to consider this before you commit.</p>



<p>The reason I say this is because once you&#8217;ve accepted the family will move on to make their other arrangements that are based in part on your commitment to attend.&nbsp;<strong>If you call at the last minute to cancel, it will be near impossible to replace you.</strong></p>



<p>Look at your schedule and make sure there is nothing to prevent you from fulfilling your role as a PB before you commit.&nbsp;<strong>There is absolutely nothing wrong with turning down the opportunity if you can not make arrangements to be there.</strong></p>



<p>It is actually the most honorable thing you can do in those circumstances. The family would much rather receive an honest &#8220;no&#8221; than to have a wishy-washy &#8220;yes&#8221;. &#8220;Let your yes be yes and your no be no.&#8221;</p>



<h2><strong>2. Get a hair cut</strong></h2>



<p>If you have attended any funerals in your life then you have likely seen the person who looked like they rolled out of bed and came to the service. Trust me when I say that you do not want to do this as a PB.</p>



<p><strong>Make sure you are groomed before you attend.</strong>&nbsp;That means spending some time taking a bath, combing your hair, trimming your beard, and possibly shaving. Save your sexy stubble for date night with your wife.</p>



<p>Don&#8217;t be afraid to reach for the cologne bottle and deodorant as well. Now look, don&#8217;t take a bath in your perfume. You want just enough to smell good. If you start with bathing, you will find it doesn&#8217;t take that much cologne to smell good.</p>



<p>This may all seem very obvious but you would be surprised. Common sense isn&#8217;t so common anymore. The key is to look your best. Pretend your picture is going to be taken afterward if you have to.</p>



<p>Once you step into the funeral home as a PB you are a representation of the family. We want to make sure that we make the best impression we can with visitors and other family members.&nbsp;<strong>The extra care you take in your appearance will communicate your respect.</strong></p>



<p></p>



<h2><strong>3. Get a suit</strong><br></h2>



<p>Very closely associated with your &#8220;shave and a hair cut&#8221; is the clothes you wear. In some cases, the family may have made arrangements for the PBs to wear a certain style of suit or tux. This is not typically the case.</p>



<p>In most circumstances, you will need to provide your own suit. Yes, you need to get a suit if you don&#8217;t have one.&nbsp;<strong>The style needs to be business formal.</strong>&nbsp;Don&#8217;t wear a tux unless otherwise directed by the family.</p>



<p>A plain black suit with a black tie is perfectly acceptable. If you do not wish to wear all black, then wear a black tie with a black blazer. Blue jeans are not appropriate unless it&#8217;s all you can afford. If you bring that fact to the attention of the family they may help provide you with a suit.</p>



<p>&#8220;Why black?&#8221; you ask. Well, again a PB you are representing the family.&nbsp;<strong>The traditional color of a family that is grieving is black.</strong>&nbsp;If you take issue with wearing black, then speak with the person that invited you to get instructions on what is an acceptable alternative.</p>



<p>There are many resale and discount clothing stores where you can find perfectly good suits for a very reasonable price. Slacks and blazers are passable if you have them already. Again, I would suggest you endeavor to get a suit.</p>



<p><strong>Being a PB is an honorable role in the service.</strong> You can show the family how much you appreciate the invitation by spending a little money on some nice clothes in return.</p>



<h2><strong>4. No new girlfriends</strong></h2>



<p>A funeral home is not a place to bring your new girlfriend. You may be very proud of her and she is probably a very nice person, but it is very tacky. Unless she is your fiance&#8217; it may be better to fly solo.</p>



<p><strong>We don&#8217;t want to draw attention away from the family and the departed.</strong>&nbsp;Bringing your new squeeze is likely to create a lot of waves. It may not even be negative attention. The fact is, that you and your girlfriend may pull the focus away from what is important. The family.</p>



<p>Now, I say this with some grace because quite a few couples these days choose to date for long periods before they either become engaged or get married. In those cases, your girlfriend may have a long-standing relationship with the family and it would be no different than bringing your wife in that regard.</p>



<p>Just make sure that is the case and it is indeed appropriate to bring her with you. There is nothing wrong with asking permission from the family either. If they say it is ok then it&#8217;s ok. The point is to err on the side of being respectful.</p>



<p>You also want to consider that your new girlfriend will likely not know anyone and will be very uncomfortable away from your presence. This could prove to be a distraction for you in performing your role as a PB. You may miss your queues tending to her needs if you aren&#8217;t careful.</p>



<h2><strong>5. Be on time</strong></h2>



<p>Speaking of missing your queues, the only thing worse is for you to show up late. If you&#8217;re running behind schedule getting to the visitation, it may slide with the family. However, being late to the funeral service is never acceptable as a PB.</p>



<p><strong>This is the most significant event in the family&#8217;s life to this point, and when you are late it communicates an attitude of indifference. </strong>Basically, you are saying that this wasn&#8217;t important enough to you for you to plan ahead.</p>



<p>Being punctual to both the visitation and the funeral service will send the appropriate message. It will tell the family in so many words that you cared so much that you made sure not to allow any interruptions to keep you from being there for them.</p>



<p><strong>Non-verbal communication comprises about 80% of all communication between people.</strong>In light of that fact, the very last message we want to send to the family is that we do not care. We care very much about them and for them in this time of grieving.</p>



<p>Being on time for both the visitation and the funeral is an excellent way to tell the family just that. You know that your presence is desirable because of the invitation to be a PB. So use the opportunity to &#8220;pay your respects&#8221; by being on time.</p>



<h2><strong>6. Get instructions for yourself</strong></h2>



<p><strong>Each and every funeral home is going to strive to make this the best experience possible for the grieving family.</strong>&nbsp;Making sure that the PBs know how vital their role is and how to perform it with precision is no exception to that.</p>



<p>In all of my personal experiences, I have never seen the funeral home staff miss the opportunity to pull the PBs aside for a private meeting to give them the order of events. It is always in the staff&#8217;s best interest to make sure that PBs know exactly what to do and when to do it.</p>



<p><strong>Any interruption or mishap during the service will likely raise questions with the family as to what happened. </strong>Especially those members who are super vigilant about such interruptions. After all, funerals are not cheap and we all want to receive the very best value for our money.</p>



<p>In light of that, most funeral homes strive to ensure that there are zero unexpected wrinkles in the order of the service. That means you will be able to count on the staff to lead you in the right direction no matter what type of service you are PBing for.</p>



<p>Any member of the funeral home staff will be able to answer your questions in detail and walk you through step by step scenario. These instructions may vary depending on what type of arrangements the family has made for the service. Therefore, rely on their expertise.</p>



<p><strong>If you have questions direct them to the staff or the director of the funeral home.</strong>&nbsp;Just because your uncle is the honorary PB doesn&#8217;t mean he was listening perfectly during the meeting. Get your information first hand. It may save you embarrassment.</p>



<h2><strong>7. A servant&#8217;s heart</strong></h2>



<p>Ok. Let&#8217;s recap. You have accepted, bathed, shaved, dressed, arrived on time, and received your instructions. Now what?&nbsp;<strong>Make yourself available to serve the family in any way you can.</strong></p>



<p>This will be your primary function during the visitation. You will likely be sitting for most of the funeral depending on the type of service with the exception of performing your PB duties. However, you will have a great opportunity during the visitation to serve.</p>



<p>I&#8217;ll cover briefly some of the things you could do here but if you want a detailed look at what you can do at the visitation check out my article &#8220;What do you do at a visitation&#8221;.</p>



<p>It is always a good idea for you to &#8220;pay your respects&#8221; to the family as soon as you arrive at the visitation. This will allow you to ask how you can be of service to them. They may have you speak with one of the other PBs or they may tell you themselves.</p>



<p>Do as you are directed and do not disappear. The point of you being invited was for you to be present. You may find yourself doing other things to help out such as:</p>



<ul><li>Greeting</li><li>Taking out trash</li><li>Cleaning</li><li>Escorting the elderly</li><li>Fetching things</li></ul>



<p>etc&#8230;</p>



<p>The whole point is to be a servant while you are at the funeral home. If you need to, pretend you are a new member of the funeral home staff. The flunky. You get the jobs nobody else wants and that&#8217;s ok. You are not here for you but for the family.<strong>Do it with a smile.</strong></p>



<p>You may not be asked to do much or may not be asked to do anything at all. If that&#8217;s the case be vigilant to look for ways you can help regardless. In between serving you should be visiting and friendly with other folks.&nbsp;<strong>This is a great opportunity to pay your respects by serving in any way you can.</strong></p>



<h2><strong>8. Behave yourself</strong></h2>



<p>As you make your way around the funeral home to visit and interact with people, be mindful of your body language and your tone. As mentioned earlier, non-verbal communication is 80% of all communication. <strong>We don&#8217;t want to unintentionally send the wrong message.</strong></p>



<p>Again, if you need to, conduct yourself as though you were a member of the funeral home staff. Once you put the PB decoration on, you immediately become a representation of the family and the funeral home.</p>



<p>You simply want to make sure that your conduct reflects both parties in an honorable way. Don&#8217;t be the guy telling dirty jokes in the hallway right outside the viewing room.<strong> PB</strong>s<strong> need to be exemplary in how they carry themselves. </strong>This would include silencing your phone and checking it only as needed.</p>



<p>This would not be the appropriate time to see if you can beat your record score on &#8220;candy crush&#8221;. If you are feeling bored, it may be time to once again see if there is anything you can do to serve.</p>



<p>When it comes to the actual funeral service, there should be a pretty regimented order of events. This won&#8217;t leave you with much idle time. If you are quiet and follow the instructions given to you by the staff, things will likely go pretty smoothly. Behave as if Jesus was present and you should be fine.</p>



<h2><strong>9. Pay attention</strong></h2>



<p>Now the time has come for you to bring your best game. Do not let yourself be distracted during the funeral service. The ques that you get may not be very obvious. So pay attention to the staff and your fellow PBs.</p>



<p>As I mentioned earlier, any hiccup in the service from inattention is likely to make waves with the family. We do not want that to happen simply because we were daydreaming or playing with our phones.&nbsp;<strong>A good rule of thumb with your phone is to purpose not to check it once the funeral has begun.</strong></p>



<p>You will have the opportunity to glance at it later. As the funeral service comes to a close your focus needs to be on fulfilling your role as a PB. After all, that is the reason you are here.</p>



<p>Depending on the type of service you will be participating in, services can last between 30-60 minutes. This greatly depends on the wishes of the family and the number of speakers, songs, poems, and such. There may even be a photo slide.</p>



<p>If you become emotional at any point during the service that is absolutely fine. Being a PB does not mean being a robot. Grieve as you feel you need to and then compose yourself so you do not miss your ques. There will be more opportunities for you to have closure at the graveside service.</p>



<p>One more thing I want to mention here.&nbsp;<strong>Once you are at the gravesite, watch your step.</strong>&nbsp;You will be helping to lift the casket which is likely to be heavy. Make sure you have a solid footing with each step. The last thing you want to do is to get unintentionally injured while serving.</p>



<h2><strong>10. Say your goodbyes</strong></h2>



<p>Once you have performed your duty as a PB to help put the casket in place you aren&#8217;t completely done.&nbsp;<strong>You will want to show respect by staying for the entire graveside service and possibly shake hands with those who have attended.</strong></p>



<p>Now, do this only as the opportunity presents itself. This will not be like leaving the church where the pastor stands at the back thanking everyone for coming. You mainly want to make sure that you thank the family for involving you and express what an honor it was.</p>



<p>Be sensitive to the atmosphere here though. If the family is overcome with grief, this may not be the appropriate time. You may want to let them grieve and express your thanks at a later date. This greatly depends on your relationship with the family.</p>



<p>The point of staying a few minutes after the service has concluded is that we don&#8217;t want to be seen running off. Take the time to thank the staff if they are still present. Shake hands with your fellow PBs. All of you are likely breathing a sigh of relief that nothing went wrong.</p>



<p>Most importantly, make sure you have had the appropriate time to say goodbye to your loved one in your own way. As you remove your PB decoration, say a prayer and thank God for the opportunity to do this. Allow yourself to grieve and get the closure you need. After all, this was a loss for you as well.</p>



<p>In conclusion, if you want to be the best PB you can be all you need to have is to have the utmost respect for the family and the departed. Also, never hesitate to ask us any questions. <strong>We are here to serve you.</strong></p>



<p>&#8220;Blessed are those who mourn, for they shall be comforted&#8221; Matt 5:4</p>



<p>Article contributed by: Jason Coker</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wonderful-kare-161424.netlify.app/10-essential-pointers-to-be-an-excellent-pallbearer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
